
• Most common arrangement is 2 wheels • Mounting wheels to motors or wheels
on opposite sides of the base, with 1 or to shaft is the hardest part of building
2 casters or skids for balance. Typical a wheeled base. R/C servo motors
variations include 4- and 6- wheeled provide a consistent means for
bases. These do not require balancing mounting small wheels to them, so
casters/skids. these types of motors are quite
• Size of wheel greatly influences common in small mobile robots.
traveling speed of robot. Larger wheels • Modest degree of accuracy needed
(for a given motor speed) make the in mounting the wheels to avoid
robot go faster. run- out, side- to- side wobble as the
• On 2- wheeled robots with support wheel rotates.
caster/skid, the wheels can be
mounted centerline in the base or
offset to the front or back.
• Distance measuring (odometry) more
reliable with wheeled bases. Accurate
travel distance calculations are difficult
with tracked and legged robots.

Wheel Diameter and Width
There are no standards among wheel sizes. They vary by their diameter, as well as their tread
width (the tread is the plastic, foam, or rubber material that contacts the ground).
• The larger the diameter of the wheel, the faster the robot will travel for each revolution of
the motor shaft. You can quickly calculate linear speed if you know the speed, in revolutions
per minute or second, of the motor. Simply multiply the diameter of the wheel by pi,
or 3.14, then multiply that result by the speed of the motor. See the section “Using Wheel
Diameter to Calculate the Speed of Robot Travel” for more details.
• The larger the diameter of the wheel, the lower the torque from the motor. Wheels follow
the laws of levers, fulcrums, and gears. As the diameter of the wheel increases, the amount
of torque delivered by the wheel decreases.
• Wider wheels provide a greater contact area for the wheel, and therefore traction (from
friction) is increased.
• The wider the wheels, the more the robot will tend to stay on course (called tracking). With
narrow wheels, the robot may have a tendency to favor one side or the other when there
is even the slightest misalignment of the wheels. Conversely, if the wheels are too wide, the
friction created by the excess wheel area contacting the ground may hinder the robot’s
ability to make smooth turns.
When selecting the wheel diameter and width, match the wheel to the job. A robot with
modest- size wheels of fairly narrow proportions (say, 1/4″ wide for a wheel of 2.5″ to 3″ in
diameter) will be more agile than if it were equipped with much wider wheels.
Wheel Placement and Turning Circle
Where the wheels are located on the robot base affects the turning circle of the robot. Whenever
possible, locate the wheels within the body of the base, rather than outside it. This
decreases the effective size of the robot and allows it to turn in a tighter circle. Figure 26- 3
shows wheels mounted both within the area of the base and outside it.

The exact shape of the base is not relevant to the function of the
robot, though for best results smooth or round contours work best. The
corners of square robots can snag on furniture and other objects. Though
it’s a bit more work, smoothing out the shape of the base provides a more
streamlined look, and it allows the robot to navigate more easily, and with
less potential damage to its surroundings.



motor sheild
http://playground.arduino.cc/Main/AdafruitMotorShield